使い捨てる[つかいすてる]:to use and then throw away, 人工衛星[じんこうえいせい]:man-made satellite
（ナレーション）
使い捨てられた人工衛星
Abandoned artificial satellites.
Tanks jettisoned from shuttles.
シャトル:shuttlecock, 切り離す[きりはなす]:to detach/to decapitate/to cut loose, タンク:tank (of liquid)
シャトルが切り離したタンク
ステーション:station, 建造[けんぞう]:building/construction, 廃棄物[はいきぶつ]:waste matter/waste/garbage
ステーション建造時に出た廃棄物
Refuse generated during
space station construction.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, スペース:space (room, area, outer space), デブリ:debris
これら 宇宙のゴミ
スペースデブリは―
This junk, space debris, is traveling around
the Earth at speeds approaching 8 kilometers per second.
秒速[びょうそく]:per second, キロメートル:kilometer/kilometre, 近い[ちかい]:near|close (in time)|close (relationship)||, 速度[そくど]:speed/velocity/rate, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 周り[まわり]:circumference/girth|surroundings, 回る[めぐる]:to go around|to return|to surround|, 回る[まわる]:to turn|to visit several places|to function well|
秒速８キロメートル近い速度で
地球の周りを回っています
デブリ:debris, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, ぶつかる:to strike against/to collide with|to encounter
そんなデブリが
宇宙船とぶつかれば―
Should this debris collide with a spacecraft,
it could result in a terrible accident.
大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to, かねる:to be unable to/to find difficult (unpleasant, awkward, painful) to do|to serve two or more functions or roles simultaneously
大きな事故に つながりかねません
For this reason, mankind has been confronted
by the necessity of collecting this debris.
人々[ひとびと, にんにん]:each person/people/men and women, デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity, 迫る[せまる, せる]:to approach/to draw near|to press (someone for something)
そこで 人々は デブリを
回収する必要に迫られました
This is a story of 2075, a time in which
this space garbage has become a problem.
2075年―
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||, 時代[じだい]:period|the times|oldness|, 物語[ものがたり]:tale/story/legend
これは 宇宙のゴミが
問題になった時代の物語
♪～
時空[じくう]:space-time, 越える[こえる]:to cross over/to cross|to exceed, 夢を見る[ゆめをみる]:to dream/to have a dream
♪そして人は時空(とき)を
越えた夢を見る
Soshite hito wa toki wo koeta yume wo miru
And people dream dreams that transcend time.
静寂[せいじゃく, しじま]:silence/stillness/quietness, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 抱く[いだく, だく]:to embrace|to harbour (e.g. grudge)|to have sex with|
♪静寂の宇宙(うみ)に抱かれて
seijyaku no umi ni idakarete
Held in the depths of the sea.
鳥[とり]:bird|bird meat (esp. chicken meat)/fowl, 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪鳥や雲を見上げては
tori ya kumo wo miagete wa
As they look up at the stars and clouds.
儚い[はかない]:fleeting/transient|empty (dream, etc.), 生命[せいめい]:life/existence, 燃やす[もやす, もす]:to burn
♪儚(はかな)い生命(いのち)燃やした
hakanai inochi moyashita ikusen no asa ni
It set their ephemeral souls on fire on a thousand mornings.
幾[いく]:some|many|how many?, 幾[ほとほと]:quite (usu. negative connotation)/utterly/really, 千[せん, ち]:1,000/thousand, 朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||
♪幾千の朝に
光[ひかり]:light|illumination|happiness||, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
♪光が向かう場所へ
hikari ga mukau basho he habataku darou
I bet they're taking right to where the light is headed.
羽ばたく[はばたく]:to flap (wings)|to spread one's wings/to go out into the world
♪羽ばたくだろう
daichi wo ima tori yoku kette
Now kickoff from the ground like a bird.
願い[ねがい]:desire/wish/request, 放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||
♪願いを放つ時は今
hatenaki yume wo noseta furontia he
Off into the frontier that is carrying boundless dreams.
果て[はて]:the end/the extremity/the limit, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||
♪果てなき夢を乗せた
フロンティア:frontier
♪フロンティアへ
遠い[とおい]:far/distant
♪遠く遠く Dive in the Sky
tooku tooku dive in the sky
Farther and farther dive in the sky.
♪～
Phase 5
Fly Me to the Moon
Day One
I have confirmation here, too.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation, 順調[じゅんちょう]:favourable/favorable/doing well, 線[せん]:line|line (e.g. telephone line)|ray (e.g. X-ray)||, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 乗り[のり, ノリ]:riding|spread (of paints)|-seater (e.g. two-seater)|
（管制官）こちらでも確認した
順調に月への放物線軌道に乗り…
You are passing through
the outer Van Allen belt on a...
せっかく:stone burial chamber, せっかく:with trouble/at great pains|rare, 休み[やすみ]:rest|vacation|dormancy (of a silkworm prior to moulting)
（ハチマキ）
せっかくの休みなんだから―
We hardly ever get vacations!
Yuri should've come, too!
ユーリも来ればいいのに
Don't foist your own interests
off onto other people.
趣味[しゅみ]:hobby/pastime|tastes, 押しつける[おしつける]:to press/to push/to force
（フィー）
自分の趣味を押しつけるなって
Yeah, yeah...
（ハチマキ）はいはい
Wow, I can't wait!
The moon!
楽しみ[たのしみ]:enjoyment/pleasure|anticipation
（タナベ）
わあ 楽しみだなあ 月
You're allowed to take pictures
at Apollo Memorial Park, right?
アポロ:Apollo program/Project Apollo, 写真[しゃしん]:photograph/photo|movie, 撮る[とる]:to take (a photo)|to record (video, audio, etc.)/to make (a film)
アポロ記念公園って
写真 撮ってもいいんですよね？
I hear that there's a statue
of Commander Armstrong there.
船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman, 像[ぞう]:image|figure|image, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
（タナベ）アームストロング船長の
像があるらしいですけど
What are you, a tourist
or something?
観光客[かんこうきゃく]:tourist
（ハチマキ）お前は観光客かって
I guess I can't blame her.
It's her first moon trip, after all.
しかたない:it can't be helped/it's inevitable/it's no use, 初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ..., 旅行[りょこう]:travel/trip
（フィー）フッ しかたないでしょ
初めての月旅行なんだから
Still, that's no excuse for...
たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however, 記念[きねん]:commemoration/celebration/honoring the memory of something, メダル:medal
（ハチマキ）…にしたってさあ
（タナベ）ああっ 記念メダルだ
Wow, a commemorative medal!
うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!
（ウォーケン）
うわあ ああっ ああ…
（タナベ）うわっ うっ…
（ウォーケン）うわっ
I-I'm so sorry!
無重力[むじゅうりょく]:weightlessness/zero gravity, 慣れる[なれる]:to get used to|to become skilled in|to become tame
すいません
無重力は慣れてないもんで
I'm not used
to zero-G yet...
Until you are, it's a lot easier
if you move along the walls.
慣れる[なれる]:to get used to|to become skilled in|to become tame, 壁[かべ, へき]:wall|barrier|Chinese "Wall" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 伝い[づたい]:along (wall, coast, river, etc.)/alongside/following, 移動[いどう]:movement/transfer|mobile
慣れるまでは
壁伝いに移動したほうがいいですよ
I'm so sorry!
ほんと:truth/reality|proper, あああ:Aah!/Ooh!/Oh No!
ほんとに すいませんでした
ああっ あああ…
思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
誰かさんを思い出すな
（タナベ）ん？
Gee, he reminds me
of someone I know...
He reminds me of somebody, too.
Say, from three years ago?
思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
（フィー）私も思い出すな ３年前
（ハチマキ）ううっ…
I guess everybody's got a past,
huh, Senpai?
歴史[れきし]:history, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
人に歴史ありですね 先輩
記念[きねん]:commemoration/celebration/honoring the memory of something, メダル:medal, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
あの… その記念メダルください
Excuse me, I'd like one of those
commemorative medals, please.
Of course.
Thank you.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, ござる:to be
（係員）
はい ありがとうございます
（タナベ）あれ？
（ハチマキ）あっ どうした？
Huh?
What's wrong?
Huh? Where did l...
あれ？ なんで…
財布[さいふ]:purse/handbag/wallet, 部屋[へや]:room|apartment|stable, 置く[おく]:to put|to leave (behind)|to establish (an organization, a facility, a position, etc.)||, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
お財布 部屋に
置いてきちゃったみたいです
It looks like I left my wallet in my cabin.
For the love of...
ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation)
ったくよ
（タナベ）ん？
ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation)
ったくよ
（タナベ）ん？
（乗客たち）おおっ！
We thank you for choosing
to fly with us.
度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol), 本船[ほんせん]:mother ship/this ship, 利用[りよう]:use/utilization/utilisation, いただく:to receive/to get|to eat
（船長）
この度は本船をご利用いただき―
誠[まこと]:truth|sincerity|that's right (used when recalling forgotten information, suddenly changing the subject, etc.), ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, ござる:to be
誠にありがとうございます
I am your captain, Kenji Impadi.
船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman, 申す[もうす]:to say/to be called|to do
私 船長の
ケンジ･インパディと申します
We have cleared the Van Allen belt,
and will now begin normal cruising.
本船[ほんせん]:mother ship/this ship, 帯[おび, たらし]:obi/kimono sash|paper wrapper on books, CDs, etc., 帯[たい]:band (e.g. conduction, valence)/belt (e.g. Van-Allen, asteroid, etc.), 抜ける[ぬける]:to come out|to fade|to wear a hole (e.g. clothes)||, 通常[つうじょう]:common/general/normal, 航行[こうこう]:cruise/navigation/sailing, 移る[うつる]:to move (house)|to change the target of interest or concern|to elapse (passage of time)||
本船は バーガレン帯を抜け
通常航行へと移ります
Excuse me, I heard that the way you use the
restroom is different when the ship is underway.
We will do all we can to make our four-day
flight to the moon a safe one,
日間[ひあい]:number of days/period of days|daily interest rate, 日間[にっかん]:daytime/during the day, 安全[あんぜん]:safety|security, 航行[こうこう]:cruise/navigation/sailing, 務める[つとめる]:to work (for)|to serve (as)|to conduct a religious service, まいる:to go/to come|to be defeated
月までの４日間
安全航行に務めてまいりますので…
...and we look forward
to our time with you.
悔しい[くやしい, くちおしい]:vexing/annoying/frustrating
（母親）だって悔しいじゃない
It's frustrating, that's all!
Our factory was in business for three generations!
工場[こうじょう, こうば]:factory/plant/mill, 代[しろ]:substitution|material|price||, 代[よ]:world/society/age, 続く[つづく]:to continue|to continue (without a break)|to occur again and again||, 老舗[しにせ, ろうほ]:old shop/shop of long standing|well-established
うちの工場は
３代続いた老舗なのよ
製品[せいひん]:manufactured goods/finished goods/product, 恥ずかしい[はずかしい]:shy/ashamed|disgraceful, 物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
製品だって どこに出しても
恥ずかしくない物 作ってるのに
We could hold our heads high, no matter
where we sent our products, so why...?!
しかたない:it can't be helped/it's inevitable/it's no use
（父親）しかたないだろ
What else
could we do?!
We can't get the gasoline we need
to run our equipment anymore!
機械[きかい]:machine/mechanism|instrument, 動かす[うごかす]:to move|to inspire|to change||, 原油[げんゆ]:crude oil, 手に入る[てにはいる]:to obtain/to come into possession of/to get hold of
（父親）機械 動かす原油が
もう手に入らないんだ
Even if we could, it would
add too much to our costs!
たとえ:example|simile/metaphor, たとえ:even if/no matter (what)/if, たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however, コスト:cost, かかる:to span/to bridge/to cross, かかる:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by
たとえ入ったって
コストが かかり過ぎる
The only people who would
lend money to people like us to buy new machinery
are those thugs.
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 機械[きかい]:machine/mechanism|instrument, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
新しい機械を買うにも―
みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 資金を出す[しきんをだす]:to provide with funds/to fund/to advance some capital
俺たちみたいなのに
資金を出してくれるのは―
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), 連中[れんちゅう, れんじゅう]:company/lot|troupe
あんな連中しかいない
Those people won't chase us
all this way, will they?
連中[れんちゅう, れんじゅう]:company/lot|troupe, 追いかける[おいかける]:to chase/to run after/to pursue
あの連中 ここまでは
追いかけてこないわよね？
No...
（父親）ああ
Who was it who discovered resources
out here in space, anyway?
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 資源[しげん]:resources, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
宇宙資源なんて
誰が見つけたんだろう
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 決める[きめる]:to decide|to clinch (a victory)|to persist in doing||
（父親）ああ だから
宇宙で死のうって決めたんだ
That's why we decided
to die in space.
It'll be easier on Sia that way.
シアだって そのほうがいいさ
You're right.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 大好き[だいすき]:loveable/very likeable/like very much
そうね
この子 宇宙が大好きだものね
She loves space,
doesn't she?
（女性の悲鳴）
（ハチマキ）あっ…
No!
（女性）いやーっ
（ハチマキ）あっ
There's no escape for you,
little lady!
逃がす[にがす]:to set free/to let go|to miss (e.g. a chance), お嬢[おじょう]:(someone else's) daughter, 捕まえる[つかまえる]:to catch/to arrest/to seize
（男性）逃がさないよ お嬢さん
フフフ… ほら 捕まえた
See, I've already
caught you!
キャーッ！
（男性）ぐはっ
（女性）あっ
（男性）あっ… がはっ うう…
You jerk!
What the hell
do you think you're doing?!
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places
てめえ こんな所まで来て
何やってんだ！
う… うわっ ぐぐっ うう
（ハチマキ）ヘヘッ
（男性）うわっ
Cut! Cut!
カット:cut/cutting
（監督）カーット！ カット
（ハチマキ）えっ？
You moron! This is supposed
to be a closed set!
このバカ！
トウシロが入ってきてるじゃねえか
I-I'm sorry, Director...
監督[かんとく]:supervision/control|director
（ＡＤ）す… すいません 監督
監督？
"Director"?
This is a shoot.
We're making a movie.
撮影[さつえい]:photography (still or motion)/photographing/filming, 映画[えいが]:movie/film
撮影なんすよ 映画の
A movie?
Uh, you are?
映画[えいが]:movie/film
映画の… そ… そうなの？
（女優）うん
（ハチマキ）ああ…
Hey, pull yourself together!
しっかり:tightly (holding on)/firmly|strongly (built)
おい しっかりしろ
It's useless, Director,
he's out cold!
監督[かんとく]:supervision/control|director, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|, 完全[かんぜん]:perfection/completeness, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of, 失う[うしなう]:to lose/to part with
監督 駄目です
完全に 気ぃ失ってます
Suck it up!
We've still got scenes to shoot!
根性[こんじょう]:willpower/guts|character
（監督）根性 出せよ！
シーン:scene/sight, シーン:silently (as the grave)/quietly (as in death), 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
まだ シーン残ってんだぞ！
（ハチマキ）あ… ああ
部屋[へや]:room|apartment|stable, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
部屋に
忘れてきたんじゃないとなると…
Well, if you didn't leave it
in your cabin...
I guess I must have dropped
my wallet in the lounge, then...
やっぱり:too/also|still, ラウンジ:lounge, 落とす[おとす]:to drop|to clean off (dirt, makeup, paint, etc.)|to lose (a match)||, 財布[さいふ]:purse/handbag/wallet
やっぱり ラウンジで
落としたんですかね お財布
親切[しんせつ]:kindness/gentleness, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather
親切な人が
拾ってくれてるといいけどね
I hope some kind soul finds it
and turns it in for you.
ハァ… どうしよう
What am I gonna do...?
Excuse me, has anyone turned in
a wallet to the lost and found?
財布[さいふ]:purse/handbag/wallet, 落とし物[おとしもの]:lost property/something dropped and left behind, 届く[とどく]:to reach|to be attentive|to be delivered
（タナベ）すみません
財布の落とし物 届いてませんか？
A wallet, miss? In that case,
please give me your ID number...
財布[さいふ]:purse/handbag/wallet, お客様[おきゃくさま]:guest/visitor|customer, ナンバー:number
（係員）財布ですか？
では お客様のＩＤナンバーを…
I can't see anything
at all!
見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
（シア）何も見えないよ？
That's strange...
おかしい:funny/amusing|strange
（父親）おかしいな
It doesn't have a lens cap,
so it can't be that...
付く[つく]:to be attached|to remain imprinted|to bear (fruit, interest, etc.)||, 付く[づく]:to become (a state, condition, etc.)
ふたが付いてるわけじゃないし
Maybe it's not focused...
ピント:focus point/focus, 合う[あう, おう]:to come together|to fit|to be profitable|
（父親）
ピントが合ってないのかな？
Or maybe it's broken.
壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through
壊れてるのかも
（シア）ええっ うそだ
You're kidding!
見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
あっ 見えた！
I see something!
（母親･父親）えっ？
（シア）わーい 月だ 月
Yay, it's the moon!
It's the moon!
有料[ゆうりょう]:toll/fee/charge
（母親）あっ…
（タナベ）これ 有料なんですよ
These cost money.
ど… どうも
T-Thank you.
Are you on vacation?
旅行[りょこう]:travel/trip
（タナベ）ご旅行ですか？
Yes.
ええ…
（母親）ええ まあ…
Yes, sort of...
Oh, let me repay you...
お金[おかね]:money
ああ お金
That's okay,
don't worry about it.
気にする[きにする]:to mind (negative nuance)/to care about/to worry, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
あっ いいんですよ
気にしないでください
気にする[きにする]:to mind (negative nuance)/to care about/to worry, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
あっ いいんですよ
気にしないでください
"That's okay,
don't worry about it!"
I'm sorry,
I'll pay you back!
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|
す… すみません
あとで ちゃんと返しますから
Still, if we haven't found it here,
either, that must mean...
見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered
しかし
ここでも見つからないとなると…
Do you really think
it was stolen?
やっぱり:too/also|still, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
やっぱり
取られちゃったんでしょうか？
世の中[よのなか]:society/the world/the times, 親切[しんせつ]:kindness/gentleness, ばかり:only/merely|approximately
まあ 世の中
親切な人ばかりじゃないからね
Well, not everybody in the universe
is a sweetheart, you know?
And what the heck
is keeping Hachimaki?
ハチマキ:headband, 遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|
それにしても ハチマキ 遅いな
（タナベ）あっ そうですね
Hey, you're right!
コンテナ:container (e.g. shipping)/skip
コンテナのほうとか
捜しに行ってくれたはずですけど
I think he said he was going
to look around the cargo area or something.
しょう:workman/artisan|craft, しょう:quotient|dealing/dealer, 私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us
（フィー）
しょうがない 私たちも行くか
I guess we'd better go
look over there, then.
Right.
（タナベ）はい それじゃ
Bye, then.
Thank you.
どうも
（シア）バイバーイ
Bye bye!
バイバーイ
How many days will it be 'til we
get to the moon? I can't wait...!
いくつ:how many?|how old?, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||, 着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow, 楽しみ[たのしみ]:enjoyment/pleasure|anticipation
あと いくつ寝たら
月に着くのかな 楽しみ
（母親）ううっ…
代わり[かわり]:substitute|stand-in|compensation||, 代わり[がわり]:substitute for ...
（ハチマキ）
でえっ 俺が代わりに？
You want me
to take his place?!
What choice do we have?
We can't keep filming with him like that!
しょう:workman/artisan|craft, しょう:quotient|dealing/dealer, 続ける[つづける]:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
しょうがねえだろ
あれじゃ 続けられねえからな
Maybe so, but still...
そう言われてもさ
顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face, オオカミ:wolf (Canis lupus)
ああ 顔は
ＣＧでオオカミにしちゃうんで―
We'll use CG to turn your face
into a wolf's, so don't worry.
心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care
心配ないっすよ
Yeah, but I've never
acted in anything before.
芝居[しばい]:play/drama, なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something
けど俺 芝居なんかしたことないし
What's that got to do with anything?
関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
そんなの関係ねえって
To play a werewolf, you just need to go by instinct!
本能[ほんのう]:instinct, オオカミ:wolf (Canis lupus)
本能のままに
オオカミ男やってくれりゃあな
Right, go by instinct.
本能[ほんのう]:instinct
そう 本能のままにね
ほ… 本能って…
Instinct for what?
スペース:space (room, area, outer space), ウルフ:wolf
（ＡＤ）はい
「スペースウルフ 月に行く」
Okay! Space Wolf Goes to the Moon!
Scene 7, take 18!
シーン:scene/sight, シーン:silently (as the grave)/quietly (as in death), カット:cut/cutting
シーン７ カット18
And... action!
本番[ほんばん]:performance|game|actual sexual intercourse (i.e. not simulated), スタート:start
（監督）本番 スタート
（ハチマキ）ええっ
Hey, you're as stiff as a board, buddy!
Relax, relax!
硬い[かたい]:hard|stiff|strong||, 彼氏[かれし]:boyfriend
（ＡＤ）はいはい 硬いよ 彼氏
リラックス:relax
リラックス リラックス
かっ うう…
You're an animal!
けだもの:beast/brute/animal
けだものだ
いっ…
You're turning into a lone wolf!
匹[ひき, き]:counter for small animals|counter for rolls of cloth (two han in size)|counter for horses|, けだもの:beast/brute/animal
お前は１匹の けだものになるんだ
腹をすかす[はらをすかす]:to be hungry, けだもの:beast/brute/animal
そう 腹をすかした
けだものなんだよ
That's right, you're a hungry beast!
And right there in front of you
is a tasty little bunny!
おいしい:delicious/tasty|attractive, ウサギ:rabbit/hare/coney
目の前にいるのは
おいしそうなウサギちゃんだ
デリシャス:delicious, 我慢[がまん]:patience/endurance/perseverance
ウ～ デリシャス
もう我慢できない
Mmm, delicious!
You can't hold yourself back anymore!
A nice, cute,
first-rate dinner!
ナイス:nice, キュート:cute, 最高[さいこう]:most/highest|best, ディナー:dinner
ナイスでキュートな
最高のディナーだ
If you don't catch her quickly,
she'll get away!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 捕まえる[つかまえる]:to catch/to arrest/to seize, 逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
早く捕まえないと
逃げられちまうぞ～
ああ… ウガアアーッ
ウーン:hmm/well, ナイス:nice
ウーン ナイス！
Nice one!
助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|
（ハチマキ）ガアーッ！
（女優）いやーっ！ 助けてー
No! Save me!
（タナベ）ええっ！？
（ハチマキ）ガルルル…
No!
（女優）いやーっ！
（ハチマキ）んぐっ… ああ
（女優）えっ？
What do you think
you're doing?!
何やってんですか！
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, がさつ:crude/unrefined|ill-mannered, 乱暴[らんぼう]:rude/violent/rough
先輩が がさつで乱暴なのは
分かってましたけど―
I knew you were rude and violent, but I didn't
think you were capable of this, Senpai!
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
まさか こんなことするなんて！
Cut! Cut!
カット:cut/cutting
カット！ カット
えっ？
Don't jump to conclusions, damn it!
They're shooting a movie!
勘違い[かんちがい]:misunderstanding/wrong guess, こりゃ:hey there/I say/see here, 映画[えいが]:movie/film, 撮影[さつえい]:photography (still or motion)/photographing/filming
（ハチマキ）勘違いすんなよ
こりゃ 映画の撮影だ
I'm sorry, our leading man got hurt,
so I asked him to fill in.
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 男優[だんゆう]:actor (male)
悪いねえ
男優がケガしちゃったもんで―
代役[だいやく]:substitute (e.g. actor)/substitution/stand-in, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself, たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however
彼に代役 お願いしたってわけ
See?
なっ
I-I'm so sorry!
I just assumed...
なさる:to do, てっきり:surely/certainly/beyond doubt
ご… ごめんなさい 私 てっきり…
You assumed what?
てっきり:surely/certainly/beyond doubt
（ハチマキ）てっきり 何だよ？
ふーん:hmm/well ...|roughly, 映画[えいが]:movie/film
ふーん 映画ねえ
Gee, a movie, huh?
Yeah.
ああ うおっ…
Do you have
a movie permit?
撮影[さつえい]:photography (still or motion)/photographing/filming, 許可[きょか]:permission/approval|to permit, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
撮影の許可 取ってんの？
Gimme back
my camera!
カメラ:camera, 返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|
（監督）カメラ 返せよ
Wow, you'll never get permission
for something like this...
許可[きょか]:permission/approval|to permit, 取れる[とれる]:to come off|(of pain, a fever, etc.) to disappear|to be caught||
おお…
これじゃあ 許可 取れないわ
That puts food on our tables!
飯[めし]:cooked rice|meal|one's livelihood, 飯[まんま, まま]:cooked rice, 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
（監督）
俺たちゃ それで飯 食ってんだ
んぐっ あいたたたた…
I'm so sorry we interfered
with your "art."
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 芸術[げいじゅつ]:(fine) art/the arts, 邪魔[じゃま]:hindrance|to visit (somebody's home)|demon who hinders Buddhist training
悪(わり)いねえ
あんたたちの芸術 邪魔しちゃって
警備員[けいびいん]:guard/security (officer)/guardsman, 連絡[れんらく]:to contact|contacting|connection|
タナベ 警備員に連絡して
（監督）えっ？
Tanabe, call security
and let them know about this.
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, ねえさん:elder sister|(vocative) young lady
テクノーラの社員なんだよ
その ねえさん
The nice lady there
is a Technora employee.
Senpai, so are we...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us
先輩 私たちもですよ
We'll look after your equipment
until we reach the moon. Good day.
着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow
（チェンシン）月に着くまで―
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 機材[きざい]:machine parts/machinery/equipment, 預かる[あずかる]:to look after|to take charge of|to reserve (judgment), いただく:to receive/to get|to eat
こちらの機材は
預からせていただきます では
We're really sorry
about that.
（監督）どうも すいません
全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 取り上げる[とりあげる]:to pick up|to adopt|to take away|
全部 取り上げられちゃったわね
They took all
our equipment...
What are we
gonna do now?
（男優）どうすんです？ これから
Don't worry about it. Being a pro means
always planning ahead for the worst.
心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care
心配すんな
常[とこ]:constant/unchanging/eternal, 常[ただ, タダ]:ordinary|free of charge|unaffected||, 最悪[さいあく]:the worst|in the worst case, 事態[じたい]:situation/(present) state of affairs/circumstances, 想定[そうてい]:hypothesis/supposition/assumption
常に最悪の事態を想定しておくのが
プロってもんだ ヘヘヘッ…
♪～
Day Two
ボーッと:doing nothing|dimly|with a roar (e.g. flames), いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good
お前が ボーッとしてるから
いけないんだぞ
If you'd been paying attention,
this wouldn't have happened!
You're one to talk!
You weren't watching her, either!
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly
あなただって
ちゃんと見てなかったくせに
あっ… あの子のことだから―
Knowing her, I was positive that she'd be
looking out at space with that telescope again...
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 望遠鏡[ぼうえんきょう]:telescope, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space
きっと また望遠鏡で
宇宙を見てると思ったんだがな
Where do you suppose
she went...?
どこ行ったんだろう
Say...
（母親）ねえ
（父親）うん？
これって―
What if... What if this is a sign
that we shouldn't take her with us?
連れていく[つれていく, つれてゆく]:to take someone (to some place)/to take someone along/to lead someone away, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
あの子を連れていくなって
ことじゃないかしら
It's a little late to be saying that,
don't you think?!
今更[いまさら]:now (after such a long time)/at this late hour (i.e. it is too late for something)|afresh, 何度[なんど]:how many times?/how often?, 話し合う[はなしあう]:to discuss/to talk together, 決める[きめる]:to decide|to clinch (a victory)|to persist in doing||
今更 何言ってるんだ！
何度も話し合って決めたことだろ
We talked this over and over
before deciding to do this, remember?
そうだけど
I know, but...
Those people have even extorted money
from our relatives and friends...
親戚[しんせき]:relative/relation/kin, 知り合い[しりあい]:acquaintance, 取り立て[とりたて]:collection (of a debt)|patronage|fresh (e.g. freshly picked)
あいつら
親戚や知り合いにまで取り立てを…
Who are you saying that we
could've left Sia with?!
今更[いまさら]:now (after such a long time)/at this late hour (i.e. it is too late for something)|afresh, 預かる[あずかる]:to look after|to take charge of|to reserve (judgment), 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something
今更
シアを預かってくれる所なんか―
あるもんか！
You're right...
そうね それに―
Anyway, it would be cruel
to leave her all alone, wouldn't it?
残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save, かわいそう:poor/pitiable/pathetic
１人 残していったら
あの子がかわいそうだものね
ファニー:funny
ファニー
Fanny...
I hate space...!
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（母親）宇宙なんて
Oh, hello!
こんにちは:hello/good day (daytime greeting)
あっ こんにちは
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday
ああ 昨日はどうも
Thank you
for yesterday.
You know them?
知り合い[しりあい]:acquaintance
知り合いか？
Yes, a little.
ええ ちょっと
（父親）あの…
（タナベ）えっ？
Um...
娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman)
シアを…
娘を見ませんでしたか？
Have you seen our daughter Shia around?
You can't find her?
いないんですか？
（母親）ええ…
No...
Then we'll help you
look for her!
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
じゃあ 私たちも捜します
（ハチマキ）ええっ！？
Geez, you're always saying you'll do stuff
without thinking it through!
安い[やすい]:cheap/inexpensive|calm, 請け合い[うけあい]:assurance/guarantee
お前なあ
何でも安請け合いすんなよ
As I recall, you were standing in during
that movie shoot, right, Senpai?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 映画[えいが]:movie/film, 代役[だいやく]:substitute (e.g. actor)/substitution/stand-in
先輩だって
映画の代役やってたじゃないですか
Things just turned out
that way.
成り行き[なりゆき]:outcome/development|market order
あれは成り行きだって
I don't see her anywhere...
（タナベ）いないですね
Sia!
（父親）シア！
Where are you?
（母親）どこなの？
うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!
（ウォーケン）うわあ あっ ああ…
I-I'm sorry!
す… すいません
Hey, watch it!
気をつける[きをつける]:to be careful/to pay attention/to take care
気をつけろ！
I'm really sorry.
ほんと:truth/reality|proper
（父親）ほんと すいません
Sia!
- Sia, where are you?!
（父親）シア！
（母親）シア どこなの！
Spaceships, spaceships,
look at all the spaceships...!
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, いっぱい:one defeat, いっぱい:amount necessary to fill a container (e.g. cupful, spoonful, etc.)/drink (usu. alcoholic)|full
（シア）
♪宇宙船 宇宙船がいっぱい
They're so fun, they're so fun,
all my little spaceships!
楽しい[たのしい]:enjoyable/fun, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship
♪楽しい楽しい 私の宇宙船
フッ アハッ アハハハ…
In the rescue ball depot?
救命[きゅうめい]:lifesaving, ボール:ball, 置き場[おきば]:place for something/storehouse
（ハチマキ）救命ボール置き場？
Right. Don't you think that's the perfect
place to play hide-and-seek in?
かくれんぼ:hide-and-seek (game)/hide-and-go-seek, ちょうど:exactly/precisely|as if, ちょうど:supplies/furniture/fixtures
（タナベ）ええ かくれんぼには
ちょうどいいと思いません？
Hide and seek, huh?
かくれんぼ:hide-and-seek (game)/hide-and-go-seek
（ハチマキ）かくれんぼねえ
（シア）アハハハハ
（２人）いた！
She's here?
- Found her!
こんにちは:hello/good day (daytime greeting)
こんにちは
Hello there!
おねえちゃん:familiar form of "older sister"|form of address for young adult female
あっ おねえちゃん！
Onee-chan!
What'cha doing?
何してるの？
I'm riding
in my spaceship!
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
（シア）シアの宇宙船に乗ってんの
This isn't yours, kid.
And anyway, it isn't a spaceship.
大体[だいたい]:outline|general|in the first place, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship
お前のじゃないだろ？
大体 これは宇宙船じゃねえよ
Sure, it is!
I even gave it a name!
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 付ける[つける]:to attach|to furnish (a house with)|to wear||
宇宙船だよ
名前だって付けたんだもん
（タナベ）へえ 何て名前？
Wow, really?
What do you call it?
Um... She's the Caroline!
うんと:a great deal/very much|with a great amount of effort
うんとね
“カロリーヌ”っていうの
ふーん:hmm/well ...|roughly, ウフフ:giggle/chuckle/titter
ふーん かわいい名前だね
（シア）ウフフ…
That's a cute name.
Would you listen to me? This isn't
a spaceship, it's a rescue ball!
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 救命[きゅうめい]:lifesaving, ボール:ball
だから これは
宇宙船じゃなくて救命ボールなの
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship
違うもん シアの宇宙船だもん
Is not!
It's my spaceship!
（ハチマキ）あのなあ
Look, kid...
How do you know?
Do you have a spaceship, Onii-chan?
おにいちゃん:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
じゃあ おにいちゃんは
宇宙船 持ってるの？
ええっ…
He doesn't have any money,
so he can't buy a spaceship.
おにいちゃん:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, お金[おかね]:money, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
おにいちゃんは お金ないから
宇宙船は買えないんだよ
A girl with no wallet's got no right
to be talking down to me!
財布[さいふ]:purse/handbag/wallet, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, 偉い[えらい]:great/excellent|awful
財布 持ってないやつが
偉そうに言うな
I have one,
I just don't know where it is.
持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, 見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered
持ってないんじゃなくて
見つからないんです
I'm poor, too.
貧乏[びんぼう]:poverty/destitute/poor
（シア）シアんちも 貧乏だよ
（ハチマキ）え？
Scary guys keep coming to our house,
saying, "Give us our money!"
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid, お金[おかね]:money, 返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|
いつも怖いおじさんが
“お金 返せ！”って来るの
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, お母さん[おかあさん]:mother, かわいそう:poor/pitiable/pathetic
お父さんとお母さん
かわいそうだよ
I feel sorry for my
mommy and daddy...
（ドアの開く音）
（ハチマキ）ああ…
Sia!
（母親）シア！
Daddy! Mommy!
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, お母さん[おかあさん]:mother
（シア）お父さん お母さん
This is where
you've been?
所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places
（父親）こんな所にいたのか
Come on, let's go back
to our cabin.
お部屋[おへや]:room, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
（母親）さあ お部屋に戻ろう
（父親）どうも すいません
I'm so sorry for
all the trouble.
That's okay.
いえ
（父親）さあ シア
Come on, Sia.
Aw, but I wanna play
with them some more...!
おにいちゃん:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 遊ぶ[あそぶ, あすぶ]:to play|to mess about (with alcohol, gambling, philandery, etc.)|to be idle||, 遊ぶ[すさぶ]:to grow wild/to rage|to do something one enjoys
ええっ
まだ おにいちゃんたちと遊びたい
We're going back!
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
戻るんだ！
（シア）え？
（ハチマキ･タナベ）ああ…
Listen Sia, Mommy and Daddy want you
to take some medicine with them.
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, 薬[くすり]:medicine|efficacious chemical (gunpowder, pesticide, etc.)|(pottery) glaze|, 薬[やく]:dope/narcotics|medication, 飲む[のむ]:to drink|to smoke (tobacco)|to engulf||
なあ シア これから
お父さんたちとお薬 飲もう
痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding
なんで？ シア どこも痛くないよ
Why? I don't feel sick
or anything.
We're not taking it because we don't feel well.
We're taking it before we feel bad.
痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding, 飲む[のむ]:to drink|to smoke (tobacco)|to engulf||
痛いから飲むんじゃないんだ
その… 痛くなる前に飲むんだよ
I don't wanna!
I hate medicine!
薬[くすり]:medicine|efficacious chemical (gunpowder, pesticide, etc.)|(pottery) glaze|, 薬[やく]:dope/narcotics|medication, 嫌い[きらい]:dislike|suspicion|distinction, 嫌い[ぎらい]:dislike/hatred/fear
やだ 薬 嫌い
Don't be such
a baby, Sia.
わがまま:selfishness/egoism|disobedience
わがまま言わないで シア
But I'm not sick!
病気[びょうき]:illness/disease/sickness
だって シア 病気じゃないもん
Mommy and Daddy are going
to take it, too. Okay?
お母さん[おかあさん]:mother, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 飲む[のむ]:to drink|to smoke (tobacco)|to engulf||
お母さんたちも
一緒に飲むから ねっ？
I don't wanna!
I hate bitter stuff!
苦い[にがい]:bitter, 嫌い[きらい]:dislike|suspicion|distinction, 嫌い[ぎらい]:dislike/hatred/fear
やだ！ 苦いの嫌い
飲む[のむ]:to drink|to smoke (tobacco)|to engulf||, なさる:to do
いいから飲みなさい！
I said take it,
so just take it!
えっ！？
はっ
（父親）おい
Hey...!
I-I'm sorry, Sia...
I didn't mean to shout.
お母さん[おかあさん]:mother, 大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great, 声[こえ]:voice
ご… ごめんね シア
お母さん 大きな声 出しちゃって
It's okay...
I'll take the medicine.
ううん:no|er, well, ..., 薬[くすり]:medicine|efficacious chemical (gunpowder, pesticide, etc.)|(pottery) glaze|, 薬[やく]:dope/narcotics|medication, 飲む[のむ]:to drink|to smoke (tobacco)|to engulf||
ううん シア お薬 飲む
I'm sorry, Sia...
I'm so sorry.
ごめんね ごめんね シア
Mommy, why are you crying?
Does your stomach hurt?
お母さん[おかあさん]:mother, 泣く[なく]:to cry/to weep/to sob
お母さん なんで泣いてるの？
おなか:belly/abdomen/stomach, 痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding, 薬[くすり]:medicine|efficacious chemical (gunpowder, pesticide, etc.)|(pottery) glaze|, 薬[やく]:dope/narcotics|medication, 飲む[のむ]:to drink|to smoke (tobacco)|to engulf||, 治る[なおる]:to be cured/to get well|to get mended
おなか痛いの？
お薬 飲めば治る？
Will you feel better
if you take the medicine?
It's all right. Everything will be all right.
You're such a good girl, Sia.
大丈夫よ 大丈夫だから
シアはいい子ね
ん？ あれ？
Huh?
どうしたの？
What's wrong?
The medicine... It's gone!
薬[くすり]:medicine|efficacious chemical (gunpowder, pesticide, etc.)|(pottery) glaze|, 薬[やく]:dope/narcotics|medication
ないんだ 薬
ヘヘへヘヘ…
薬[くすり]:medicine|efficacious chemical (gunpowder, pesticide, etc.)|(pottery) glaze|, 薬[やく]:dope/narcotics|medication
おっ？ 薬？
Medicine?
Damn it, I thought there'd be something
valuable in here, and what do I find...?
金目[かねめ]:monetary value, 金目[きんめ]:Edo-period unit of gold coinage|golden eyes (of a cat, etc.)|splendid alfonsino (Beryx splendens), 期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope
チェッ 金目のもんが入ってるかと
期待してみりゃ
Oh, well.
I guess I'll go pull one more job.
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
しかたねえ もう一仕事してくるか
Day Three
Cheng-Shin-san, are you
coming off your shift?
交代[こうたい]:alternation/change/relief
（リュシー）
チェンシンさん 交代ですか？
Yes.
（チェンシン）ああ
I'm just coming off mine, too. If you like,
why not come to my cabin for some tea?
ちょうど:exactly/precisely|as if, ちょうど:supplies/furniture/fixtures, 代わる[かわる]:to succeed|to take the place of|to be exchanged
（リュシー）私も ちょうど
代わったところなんですよ
部屋[へや]:room|apartment|stable, 茶[ちゃ]:tea|tea plant (Camellia sinensis)|tea preparation||
よかったら 私の部屋でお茶でも…
（警備員）あっ チェンシンさん
ちょっと いいですか？
Cheng-Shin-san, do you
have a minute?
（チェンシン）何だ？
What is it?
It's about that movie camera
we confiscated.
例[れい]:custom|said|instance|, 例[ためし]:precedent/example, 押収[おうしゅう]:seizure/confiscation, ムービー:movie
（警備員）例の押収した
ムービーなんですが
むっ…
This is it here.
ここなんですけど
Tanabe-san?
（チェンシン）タナベさん？
No, the man in front.
奥[おく]:inner part/inside/interior
（警備員）いえ 奥の男です
Right here! Take a look.
くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one, 拡大[かくだい]:magnification/enlargement/expansion
ここ 見てください 拡大します
I'll enlarge it.
（リュシー）あっ！
件[くだん]:the aforementioned/the said|the usual, 件[けん]:matter/case/item, 貴重品[きちょうひん]:valuables/treasures, 紛失[ふんしつ]:losing something, 届[とどけ]:report/notification/registration
そういえば この２日で ６件も
貴重品の紛失届があったんですよ
Now that you mention it, we've had six reports
of lost valuables over the past two days!
えっ？
Take this man into custody
immediately!
至急[しきゅう]:urgent/pressing, 身柄[みがら]:one's person, 拘束[こうそく]:restriction/restraint/binding
至急 この男の身柄を拘束するんだ
（警備員）はっ
Yes, sir!
Excuse me, has anyone
turned in any lost items?
落とし物[おとしもの]:lost property/something dropped and left behind, 届く[とどく]:to reach|to be attentive|to be delivered
（父親）あの…
落とし物 届いてませんか？
（係員）
どういったものでしょうか？
Could you describe it?
It's a silver case
that's about this big.
くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 大きさ[おおきさ]:size/dimensions/volume, 銀色[ぎんいろ]:silver (color, colour), ケース:case (e.g. receptacle, condition, event, legal action, letter style, etc.)
このくらいの大きさの
銀色のケースなんですが
Senpai, will you treat me
to some soft-serve ice cream?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, ソフトクリーム:soft serve ice cream (icecream), おごる:to give (someone) a treat|to be extravagant/to live luxuriously
先輩 ソフトクリーム
おごってくれませんか？
Geez, would you
give it a rest?
かげん:(moon's) last quarter, かげん:lower limit|infimum
お前な いいかげんにしろよ
お金[おかね]:money
だって お金ないんですもん
But I don't have
any money!
（シア）わあ
（ハチマキ）うわあっ！
Sia-chan!
シアちゃん
おにいちゃん:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
おにいちゃん 宇宙船 買った？
Did you buy your
spaceship yet, mister?
How could I possibly have
bought one this soon?
急[きゅう]:urgent|sharp|rapid||, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
そんな急に 買えるわけねえだろ
I'll let you ride in
my Caroline, then.
乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
じゃあ シアのカロリーヌに
乗せてあげるね
I keep telling you,
that's not a spaceship.
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship
（ハチマキ）
だから あれは宇宙船じゃねえよ
What's she talking about?
どういう:somehow/how/in what way
どういうこと？
She's a fellow member of Senpai's
"personal spaceship" club.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship
先輩のマイ宇宙船仲間ですよ
Oh? She's a darn cute
club member, that's for sure.
ふーん:hmm/well ...|roughly, 随分[ずいぶん]:very/extremely|contemptible, かわいらしい:lovely/sweet
ふーん
随分 かわいらしい仲間だね
（ウォーケン）ん？
Mr. Walken?
様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
（チェンシン）ウォーケン様ですね
えっ ああ
Yeah?
I'm sorry, but would you
come with us, please?
警備員[けいびいん]:guard/security (officer)/guardsman, 同行[どうぎょう]:fellow pilgrim/fellow practicer of austerities, 同行[どうこう]:accompanying/travelling together|same bank, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
（警備員１）すいません
ちょっと ご同行 願えますか？
We won't take much of your...
手間[てま]:time/labour/labor, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
お手間は取ら…
（ウォーケン）何だよ
- What's your problem?! I'm busy!
忙しい[いそがしい, せわしい]:busy/occupied|restless
俺は忙しいんだって
あっ… チッ
警備員[けいびいん]:guard/security (officer)/guardsman
ああっ うっ
（警備員２）ああっ
警備員[けいびいん]:guard/security (officer)/guardsman
（ウォーケン）えい うっ
（警備員２）待て！
Hold it!
Don't let him
get away!
逃がす[にがす]:to set free/to let go|to miss (e.g. a chance)
逃がすな！
北極星[ほっきょくせい]:Polaris (star in the constellation Ursa Minor)/Alpha Ursae Minoris/the North Star, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
（ハチマキ）ほら
北極星のそばに見えるだろ？
See?
You can see it
right next to Polaris.
What's "Polaris"?
北極星[ほっきょくせい]:Polaris (star in the constellation Ursa Minor)/Alpha Ursae Minoris/the North Star
（シア）北極星って？
You're a spaceship nut and
you don't know what Polaris is?
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to), 北極星[ほっきょくせい]:Polaris (star in the constellation Ursa Minor)/Alpha Ursae Minoris/the North Star
お前 宇宙船好きのくせに
北極星も知らんのか？
（シア）うん
Nope.
Tell me, kid,
why do you want
a spaceship so much?
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
お前さ なんで
宇宙船 欲しいんだ？
'Cause I could go into space whenever I want!
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|
だって いつでも宇宙 行けるもん
I love space!
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 大好き[だいすき]:loveable/very likeable/like very much
シア 宇宙 大好き
あっ…
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 嫌い[きらい]:dislike|suspicion|distinction, 嫌い[ぎらい]:dislike/hatred/fear
おにちゃんは宇宙 嫌いなの？
Do you hate it
in space, mister?
I love it!
大好き[だいすき]:loveable/very likeable/like very much, ウフフ:giggle/chuckle/titter
大好きだ！
（シア）ウフフ
いよいよ:more and more/all the more|at last, ラストシーン:last scene (e.g. of a movie)
いよいよ ラストシーンすね
We're finally on the
last scene, huh?
Let's rip through it.
We're on a race against the clock.
速攻[そっこう]:swift attack/quick attack|right away, 撮る[とる]:to take (a photo)|to record (video, audio, etc.)/to make (a film), 勝負[しょうぶ]:victory or defeat/match/contest
速攻で撮りきるぞ 時間が勝負だ
Hey, I know!
（ハチマキ）そうだ！
When I get my spaceship, I'll make you my pilot.
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 手に入れる[てにいれる]:to obtain/to procure, パイロット:pilot
お前 俺が宇宙船 手に入れたら
パイロットにしてやるよ
Pilot?
パイロット:pilot
（シア）パイロット？
That's the person
who drives the spaceship.
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 運転[うんてん]:operation (of a machine, etc.)|driving|working (capital, etc.)
宇宙船を運転するんだよ
We'll blast through space at escape velocity!
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 速度[そくど]:speed/velocity/rate, ぶっ飛ばす[ぶっとばす]:to strike (as to send flying)|to jump with force|to accomplish a task very rapidly|, 楽しい[たのしい]:enjoyable/fun
第２宇宙速度で
宇宙をぶっ飛ばすんだ 楽しいぞ
It'll be great!
Yeah!
I'll be your pilot!
パイロット:pilot
うん！ シア パイロットやる
あっ あっ んぐ
（タナベ）
でも いつになりますかね それ
But when is that gonna be, I wonder?
Get off my case.
（ハチマキ）うるせえよ
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 空ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 空ける[うつける]:to become empty (hollow)|to relax from a tense situation into a vacant or absent minded state
（監督）
悪いけど そこ 空けてもらえっかな
I'm sorry, but could you let us
use that spot, please?
（ハチマキ）あ？
（監督）あっ…
Are you filming again?
撮影[さつえい]:photography (still or motion)/photographing/filming
また 撮影してるんですか？
H-How could we do that?
Our equipment was confiscated.
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
ま… まさか
撮影[さつえい]:photography (still or motion)/photographing/filming, 機材[きざい]:machine parts/machinery/equipment, 没収[ぼっしゅう]:forfeiture/seizure/confiscation, ハハハ:ha ha ha (laughter)
撮影機材は
没収されちゃってますよ ハハハ…
Is that the truth?
ほんと:truth/reality|proper
ほんとですか？
If you're going to film somewhere,
make sure you get permission first.
撮る[とる]:to take (a photo)|to record (video, audio, etc.)/to make (a film), ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 許可[きょか]:permission/approval|to permit, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
撮るなら
ちゃんと許可 取ってくださいよ
With a movie like that, though,
they'd never get permission.
映画[えいが]:movie/film, 許可[きょか]:permission/approval|to permit, 無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||
あの映画じゃ
許可は無理だろうけどね
Outta my way!
どける:to put something out of the way/to move (something, someone) aside|to remove
（ウォーケン）おら どけどけ！
役者[やくしゃ]:actor/actress
あっ あれも役者か？
Is he an actor, too?
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25)
まさか あんなやつ知りませんよ
No way! I've never seen
that guy before!
Come back here!
おとなしい:obedient/docile/quiet
待て！ おとなしくしろ
Turn yourself in!
チェンシン
Cheng-Shin?
そいつ:he/she|that, 捕まえる[つかまえる]:to catch/to arrest/to seize
ハチ そいつを捕まえてくれ！
Hachi!
Grab that guy!
（ハチマキ）
あっ ああ うわあっ…
Crap!
くっ…
（シア）ううっ…
うん？ ううっ
（シア）うわあーっ
ああっ
あっ
（フィー）くっ
貴様[きさま]:you/you bastard|you
貴様！
You bastard!
動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
（ウォーケン）
ヘヘッ みんな 動くなよ！
Stay right where
you are, people!
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself
てめえ！
Bastard!
動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
動くな！
（ハチマキ）くっ
Hold it!
Even if you do that, there's
nowhere that you can run!
ことし:this year, 逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
そんなことしたって
どこにも逃げられないぞ！
全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew
う… うるせえ！
全員 ここから出ていけ！
S-Shut your mouth!
Clear everyone out of here!
（父親）ああっ
（母親）シア！
Sia!
放す[はなす]:to release/to let go|to add (pieces of eggplant, potato, etc.) to water, broth, etc.
ああっ いや！ 放して
No! Let me go!
いやーっ…
静か[しずか]:quiet|slow|calm
し… 静かにしろ！
（シア）ひっ
B-Be quiet, damn it!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（ハチマキ）やめろ！
Don't!
Let go of the girl!
離す[はなす]:to separate/to part/to divide
（チェンシン）その子を離すんだ！
Sia!
（母親）シア！
If you value the kid's life,
do exactly as I tell you!
命[いのち]:life|lifetime|most important thing||, 命[めい]:command|life|destiny, 惜しい[おしい]:regrettable|precious|too good for|, 指示[しじ, しし]:indication/denotation|instructions, どおり:in accordance with/following|roughly
ガキの命が惜しかったら
俺の指示どおりにしろ
パイロット:pilot
まずは そこのパイロット
お前らから出ていけ！
You, the pilot there!
For starters, I want you outta here!
くっ…
Hey! You up there!
（監督）なあ あんた
（チェンシン）ん？
Would you mind using
this girl here as your hostage?
人質[ひとじち]:hostage
人質 こっちの女にしてくれんかな
ええ？
I'll pay you, okay?!
ギャラ:fee paid to performing artists, etc., ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly
（監督）
ギャラは ちゃんと出すからさ
Pay?!
ギャラ:fee paid to performing artists, etc.
（ウォーケン）ギ… ギャラって
I'm begging you! I just need to get this scene,
and my movie will be finished!
頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|, シーン:scene/sight, シーン:silently (as the grave)/quietly (as in death), 撮る[とる]:to take (a photo)|to record (video, audio, etc.)/to make (a film), 映画[えいが]:movie/film, 完成[かんせい]:complete/completion|perfection
（監督）
頼むよ このシーンさえ撮れば
映画は完成なんだ
No way! I don't want
to be a real hostage!
嫌[いや, や]:disagreeable/detestable/unpleasant, 本物[ほんもの]:genuine article/real thing/real deal, 人質[ひとじち]:hostage, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
私は嫌よ 本物の人質なんて
Idiot! You only get a chance to film a scene
with this kind of verisimilitude once in a lifetime!
（監督）バカ野郎！
臨場感[りんじょうかん]:(sense of) presence/realism/ambiance, あふれる:to overflow/to brim over/to flood, シーン:scene/sight, シーン:silently (as the grave)/quietly (as in death), めった:thoughtless/reckless|seldom (with neg. verb), 撮れる[とれる]:to be photographed|to be able to photograph
こんな臨場感あふれるシーン
めったに撮れんぞ
割り切る[わりきる]:to find a clear solution/to come to a clean decision|to divide
お前もプロなら割り切って…
If you call yourself a pro,
get in there and...
What the heck
are you saying?!
（タナベ）
こんなときに何言ってんですか！
（監督）ん？
不幸[ふこう]:unhappiness/sorrow|death (usu. of a relative), 商売[しょうばい]:trade/business/commerce, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（タナベ）
人の不幸で商売しようなんて
You're trying to make money
off of other people's misery!
If I didn't, do you think that the miserable
people would suddenly become happy?
商売[しょうばい]:trade/business/commerce, 不幸[ふこう]:unhappiness/sorrow|death (usu. of a relative), 幸福[こうふく]:happiness/blessedness/joy, 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
（監督）商売にしなかったら
不幸が幸福に変わるのかよ
問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
（タナベ）
そういう問題じゃないでしょ！
That's not the point,
and you know it!
どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
（監督）じゃあ どういう問題だよ
Then what
is the point?!
I'm saying that
there's no love in it!
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
（タナベ）
愛がないって言ってるんです
Love? How am I supposed
to make a living off of love?!
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 生活[せいかつ]:living/life (one's daily existence)/livelihood
（監督）愛だあ？
そんなもんじゃ 生活できねえだろ
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 生活[せいかつ]:living/life (one's daily existence)/livelihood
（監督）愛だあ？
そんなもんじゃ 生活できねえだろ
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 暮らし[くらし]:life/living/livelihood, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（タナベ）
愛のない暮らしなんて―
Life without love is no better than being dead!
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 暮らし[くらし]:life/living/livelihood, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（タナベ）
愛のない暮らしなんて―
- Would you two shut the hell up?!
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 暮らし[くらし]:life/living/livelihood, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（タナベ）
愛のない暮らしなんて―
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself, 黙る[だまる]:to be silent
てめえら
黙れって言ってんだろ！
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself, 黙る[だまる]:to be silent
てめえら
黙れって言ってんだろ！
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself, 黙る[だまる]:to be silent
てめえら
黙れって言ってんだろ！
変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
死んでるのと変わりません
パイロット:pilot
（ウォーケン）
そこのパイロットども
いつまで ボサッとしてんだ
You! The pilot and his buddies! How long
are you guys gonna keep standing there?!
Beat it!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
早く出てけ！
（警備員）うっ…
I'm terribly sorry, but we've temporarily
closed the observation lounge.
申し訳[もうしわけ]:apology/excuse, ただいま:Here I am/I'm home!|presently, 展望[てんぼう]:view/outlook/prospect, ラウンジ:lounge
（リュシー）申し訳ありません
ただいま 展望ラウンジは―
一時[ひととき, いっとき]:moment|former times|two-hour period, 一時[いちじ]:one o'clock|once|for a time|, 閉鎖[へいさ]:closing/closure/shutdown, いただく:to receive/to get|to eat
一時 閉鎖させて
いただいております
Lucie. Tell everyone outside the lounge
to brace for G's from a roll.
ラウンジ:lounge, 以外[いがい]:with the exception of/excepting, 全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew
（チェンシン）リュシー君
ラウンジ以外の全員に―
対[たい]:opposite|versus|to (e.g. "winning a game five to three")||, 対[つい]:pair|antithesis|counter for items that come in pairs|, ロール:roll, 指示[しじ, しし]:indication/denotation|instructions, 連絡[れんらく]:to contact|contacting|connection|
対ロールＧの指示連絡を
は… はい
Y-Yes, sir!
This is your regular check-in.
Calling Luna Ferry MO-F 57.
展望[てんぼう]:view/outlook/prospect, 室[しつ]:room|wife (of someone of high rank)|scabbard|, 室[むろ]:greenhouse/icehouse/cellar, 気圧[きあつ]:atmospheric pressure, 下げる[さげる]:to hang|to lower|to demote|
（操縦士）
展望室の気圧を下げて―
Shall I drop the pressure in the observation
lounge and knock everyone out?
気絶[きぜつ]:faint/swoon
気絶させますか
We will be handing you over to
L1 Terminal Approach momentarily.
But what if the kidnapper's
had training...?
犯人[はんにん]:offender/criminal, 訓練[くんれん]:training/drill/practice, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
（船長）
しかし 犯人が訓練していたら…
Captain. I recommend that we execute
an emergency roll maneuver.
船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman, 本船[ほんせん]:mother ship/this ship, 緊急[きんきゅう]:urgency/emergency, 回転[かいてん]:rotation (usu. around something)/revolution/turning, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 提案[ていあん]:proposal/proposition/suggestion
（チェンシン）船長
本船の緊急回転軌道を提案します
Downlink course correction
data via NavStar.
At L1 estimated
rollover point,
What? But what good
would that...
何！？ しかし…
We have Debris Section people in there.
ちょうど:exactly/precisely|as if, ちょうど:supplies/furniture/fixtures, デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 乗り合わせる[のりあわせる]:to happen to ride together/to share a vehicle/to (operate a) carpool
ちょうど デブリ課の者が
乗り合わせています
...roll your craft and initiate 0.3G deceleration
burn for 6 minutes, 30 seconds.
We can have them assist us.
協力[きょうりょく]:cooperation/collaboration, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
彼らに協力してもらって
Half Section?
半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
半課が？
（乗客たち）ああっ…
Hey! I want you people
out of here, too!
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself, とっとと:quickly/at once/right away
（ウォーケン）おら！ てめえらも
とっとと出てけってんだよ！
Are you deaf
or something?!
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
聞こえねえのか こらあ！
Please, just calm down!
I'll see to it that you're paid well!
落ち着く[おちつく]:to calm down|to calm down|to settle down (in a location, job, etc.)||, ギャラ:fee paid to performing artists, etc., 弾む[はずむ]:to spring/to bound/to bounce
（監督）ちょっと 落ち着けって
ギャラは弾むからさ
A man needs money
even in prison, right?
刑務所[けいむしょ]:prison/penitentiary, 金[おうごん, こがね]:gold, 金[かね, かな]:money|metal
刑務所ん中でも 金いるだろ？
- SHUT THE HELL UP!
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself
うるせえ！
てめえら ナメてんのか？
Are you people trying to screw with me?!
ぶっ殺す[ぶっころす]:to beat to death/to kill
本当に このガキ ぶっ殺すぞ！
（シア）うう うう
I mean it, I'll kill this kid!
Don't do it!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
やめてくれ！
Hey! Didn't I tell you not
to move unless I said so?!
勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily, 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
（ウォーケン）
おい 勝手に動くなって言ったろ
Don't you care what
happens to the kid?!
こいつがどうなってもいいのか？
Daddy! Mommy!
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, お母さん[おかあさん]:mother
お父さん お母さん
（ウォーケン）ああっ
Use me as your hostage
instead of our daughter!
娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman), 代わり[かわり]:substitute|stand-in|compensation||, 代わり[がわり]:substitute for ..., 人質[ひとじち]:hostage
娘の代わりに 私を人質にしてくれ
Give us our Sia back!
返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|
シアを返して！
Don't come any closer!
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 近づく[ちかづく, ちかずく]:to approach/to draw near|to get acquainted with, 娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman), 喉元[のどもと]:throat
それ以上 近づくな！
娘の喉元にブスリだぞ
I'll stab your kid in the throat!
This is her father saying this,
but she's such a good girl.
父親[ちちおや]:father
父親の私が言うのも何だが
その子は 本当にいい子なんだ
Just great, doting parents...
親バカ[おやバカ, おやばか]:over-fond parent/doting parent
（ウォーケン）ケッ 親バカが
貧乏[びんぼう]:poverty/destitute/poor
（父親）うちは貧乏だから―
We're a poor family, so we could
never afford to take her...
大好き[だいすき]:loveable/very likeable/like very much, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 旅行[りょこう]:travel/trip, なかなか:very/considerably|by no means (with negative verb), 連れる[つれる]:to lead/to take (a person)
大好きな宇宙旅行にも
なかなか連れていってやれなくて
...on the space vacation
that she always wanted.
But in spite of that, she says she's going
to buy a spaceship when she grows up,
大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
なのに 自分が大きくなったら
宇宙船を買うから―
...and when she does, we'll all go
on a vacation in it together.
旅行[りょこう]:travel/trip
それで旅行しようって
That's the kind of sweet girl
she is!
優しい[やさしい]:tender/kind/gentle
そういう優しい子なんだ
（シア）うう…
She's beautiful and cheerful! I'm sure she'll
make a great wife when she grows up!
美人[びじん]:beautiful woman, 明るい[あかるい]:bright|cheerful|familiar (with)|
美人だし 明るいし―
大人[おとな, だいにん]:adult, 大人[たいじん]:man of substance or virtue|giant|adult, きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 嫁[よめ]:wife/bride|(one's) daughter-in-law
大人になったら
きっと いいお嫁さんになる
Just a while ago, they went on and on
about her pictures at kindergarten!
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 幼稚園[ようちえん]:kindergarten, 絵[え]:picture/drawing/painting, 褒める[ほめる]:to praise/to admire/to speak well of someone
この間 幼稚園で絵も褒められたの
Maybe she'll become
an artist!
画家[がか]:painter/artist, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
画家になるかもしれないわ
She learned to walk before
any of the other kids!
立ち[たち]:departure|being used up|passage of time||, 人一倍[ひといちばい]:more than others/exceedingly/redoubled, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
（父親）つかまり立ちも
人一倍 早かったんだ
Maybe she'll be
a sports star!
スポーツ:sport/sports, 選手[せんしゅ]:player (in game)/team member
スポーツ選手になるかも
手先[てさき]:fingers/fingertips|underling, 器用[きよう]:skilful/skillfull|clever
ケッ 俺だって
ガキのころから手先が器用で―
Ever since I was a kid, they told me that I
had great hands so maybe I'd be a pianist!
ピアニスト:pianist
ピアニストになるとか言われてたさ
And how'd that turn out? All my nimble fingers
do is steal other people's stuff.
それがどうだ
器用[きよう]:skilful/skillfull|clever, 指[ゆび, および]:finger/toe/digit, 指[さし, サシ]:between (e.g. two people)|hindrance|arrhythmic section of recitative in noh music||, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods, かすめ取る[かすめとる]:to snatch/to steal
器用な指は
人様の物をかすめ取るだけ
You two had lots of dreams of your own
when you were kids, too, am I right?
夢[ゆめ]:dream, いっぱい:one defeat, いっぱい:amount necessary to fill a container (e.g. cupful, spoonful, etc.)/drink (usu. alcoholic)|full
あんたらだって
ガキのころは夢いっぱいだったろ
But that stuff turns out
to be lies real quick!
でも そんなもの
すぐ うそになっちまうんだよ
Artists and spaceships, all that stuff
is nothing but stupid dreams!
画家[がか]:painter/artist, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 夢[ゆめ]:dream
画家とか宇宙船とか
それこそ バカな夢だっての！
What's that moron
babbling about?
ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation)
何言ってんだ ったく…
But it'll be different
for Sia!
（父親）でも シアは違う！
No it won't!
（ウォーケン）違わねえよ！
A pathetic, worthless life
is all that's waiting for her!
辺[へん]:area|side|circumstances, 辺[へ, べ]:surrounding area|shore (of the sea)|suffix used as a rough indicator of location, direction, time, etc., 転がる[ころがる]:to roll|to fall over|to lie down||, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
その辺に転がってる
くっだらねえ人生が待ってるだけさ
Don't try to write Sia's future for her!
将来[しょうらい]:future (usually near)/prospects, 勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily, 決める[きめる]:to decide|to clinch (a victory)|to persist in doing||
シアの将来を勝手に決めるな！
Sia's future belongs
to her!
未来[みらい]:the future (usually distant)|future tense|the world to come
シアの未来は シアのものでしょ！
（父親･母親）はっ…
ああ…
タイミング:timing
分かった
タイミングはそっちでいい
Understood.
I'll leave the timing to you.
Rolling in ten seconds.
回転[かいてん]:rotation (usu. around something)/revolution/turning, 秒[びょう]:second (60th min)
回転 10秒前 ９ ８ ７
Nine.
Eight.
Seven.
Six.
６ ５ ４…
Five.
Four.
Three.
- Please, give Sia back to us!
お願い[おねがい]:request/wish|please, 返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|
（父親）
お願いだ シアを返してくれ
（チェンシン）
３ ２ １ ０
Two.
One.
Zero!
What the...?
うがつ:to drill/to bore|to hit the mark
何！？ うわっ うがっ
（シア）わあっ うう
（母親･父親）ああっ…
痛[いた]:ouch/ow/that hurt, 痛[つう]:pain/ache/-algia
（女優たち）痛っ…
（監督）ああ… たく…
Man...
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself
てめえ この！
Not so tough now, are ya...
（ウォーケン）ぐうう…
Damn, he's out cold.
伸びる[のびる]:to stretch|to make progress|to grow stale (soba)||, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
チッ 伸びてやがる
Ow...
痛[いた]:ouch/ow/that hurt, 痛[つう]:pain/ache/-algia
（母親）痛っ…
What in the world
just happened?
起きる[おきる]:to get up|to wake up|to occur (usu. of unfavourable incidents), 一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||
何が起きたんだ？ 一体
回転[かいてん]:rotation (usu. around something)/revolution/turning
（フィー）
ルナフェリーを回転させて―
They rolled the Luna Ferry to
temporarily generate gravity.
一時的[いちじてき]:temporary, 重力[じゅうりょく]:gravity/gravitation/gravitational pull, 発生[はっせい]:outbreak|generation (e.g. of power or heat)|ontogeny
一時的に
重力を発生させたんですよ
シア
（母親）シア！
Sia!
Sia!!
Daddy! Mommy!
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, お母さん[おかあさん]:mother
お父さん お母さん
（母親）ああ
Daddy! Mommy!
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, お母さん[おかあさん]:mother
（シア）お父さん お母さん
Sia!
（母親）シア！
（父親）よかった
Thank goodness!
You aren't hurt anywhere, are you?!
You must have been terrified!
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
どこも ケガしてない？
怖かったでしょ？
Wow, I'm glad that worked out.
Isn't this great, Director?
監督[かんとく]:supervision/control|director
いやあ よかった よかった
よかったすね 監督
Damn straight!
I can sell this movie for big bucks!
全く[まったく]:really|indeed|good grief (expression of exasperation), ムービー:movie, 高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive, 売れる[うれる]:to sell (well)|to be well known/to be popular
全くだ
このムービーは高く売れるぞ
Huh? What do you mean?
どういう:somehow/how/in what way
え？ どういうことすか？
I'm gonna sell it
to a news program!
ニュース:news, 番組[ばんぐみ]:program (e.g. TV)/programme, 売る[うる]:to sell
（監督）
ニュース番組に売るんだよ
This might make more money
than the movie would have!
映画[えいが]:movie/film, 銭[せん]:hundredth of a yen|coin made of non-precious materials|one-thousandth of a kan (as a unit of currency)|, 銭[ぜに]:round coin with a (square) hole in the center|coin made of non-precious materials|money
映画より
こっちのほうが銭になるかもな
You don't know when
to quit, do you?
懲りる[こりる]:to learn by experience/to learn one's lesson|to have enough (of)
懲りないねえ
Where's the kidnapper?!
犯人[はんにん]:offender/criminal
（警備員）犯人は？
ほれ
Right here.
Listen, I made a promise
with that nice guy.
おにいちゃん:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 約束[やくそく]:promise|convention|destiny
あのね
おにいちゃんと約束したんだよ
He said he'd make me his pilot
once he buys a spaceship.
おにいちゃん:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, パイロット:pilot
おにいちゃんが宇宙船 買ったら
シアをパイロットにしてくれるって
You did?
Well, you'll have to
keep your word, won't you?
約束[やくそく]:promise|convention|destiny, ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise)
そうか
約束はちゃんと守らないとな
If you're going to be a pilot,
you'll have to study very hard.
パイロット:pilot, いっぱい:one defeat, いっぱい:amount necessary to fill a container (e.g. cupful, spoonful, etc.)/drink (usu. alcoholic)|full, 勉強[べんきょう]:study|diligence|discount
パイロットになるなら
いっぱい勉強しなくちゃね
Yep! I'm gonna
work real hard!
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
うん シア 頑張る！
Sia...
- Sia...
（父親･母親）シア
痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding
（シア）
うう… 痛いよ どうしたの？
That hurts!
What's wrong?
If you're gonna work hard,
so will Daddy.
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place, お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa
頑張るから
お父さん 頑張るからな
Let's all start over from scratch.
Let's start over somewhere new.
一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, やり直す[やりなおす]:to do over again/to redo/to start over
３人で
もう一度 やり直しましょう
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
どこか新しい場所で
You're acting funny. We're on our way
to the moon right now, aren't we?
変[へん]:strange|unexpected|change||, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
（シア）変なの
これから お月様に行くのに
（父親）ああ そうか そうだな
Of course...
We are, aren't we?
Right! My wallet!
財布[さいふ]:purse/handbag/wallet
（タナベ）あっ 私のお財布！
♪～
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
飲み干す[のみほす]:to drink up/to drain (cup)
♪グッと水を飲み干し
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
夕焼け[ゆうやけ]:evening glow/red sunset/afterglow (of sunset), 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
♪今日も一日が終わって
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
街路樹[がいろじゅ]:roadside trees, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
だらけ:implying (negatively) that something is full of (e.g. mistakes)|covered all over (e.g. with blood), テンパる:to become one tile away from completion|to be at one's wits' end/to be about to blow one's fuse
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, つまずく:to stumble/to trip|to fail
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
気楽[きらく]:carefree/comfortable|easygoing
♪気楽にいこうぜ
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
愛する[あいする]:to love, 勇気[ゆうき]:courage/bravery/valour, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 叩く[たたく]:to strike|to play drums|to abuse||, 叩く[はたく]:to dust|to slap|to use up money
♪新しいドア叩いて
歩く[あるく]:to walk
♪ひとつひとつ
歩いてゆこう
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
♪君も僕もすべての人も
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
喜び[よろこび]:joy/delight/rapture, 悲しみ[かなしみ]:sadness/sorrow|affection, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
♪喜びと悲しみの意味
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), つづける:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
Next Time
The Lunar Flying Squirrels
Well, here we are.
着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow, 新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family
着いたぞ
お前の新しい家
Welcome to your new home.
（タナベ）ええ？
（ハチマキ）じゃあな
See ya.
（タナベ）ええっ
もう行っちゃうんですか？
You're leaving already?
ホテル:hotel
言ったろ？
４時にホテルだって
I told you, I have to be
at the hotel by four.
（ハチマキ）これ…
This is for you.
Oh, my!
（女性）まあ ほら これ
This is a "get-acquainted gift" from Hoshino-san!
近づき[ちかづき]:acquaintance, しるし:mark/sign|symbol, しるし:decapitated head of an enemy
星野(ほしの)さんから
お近づきのしるしにって
Open it!
開ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 開ける[ひらける]:to become opened up|to develop|to be enlightened
開けてみて
It's a pleasure to meet you,
Hoshino, my boy.
よろしく:well/properly|best regards, 頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
（サリバン）
よろしく頼むよ 星野君
I love everything
about Japan.
日本[にほん, にっぽん]:Japan
（チッタ）
私 日本って―
大好き[だいすき]:loveable/very likeable/like very much
大好きなんです
What are you thinking?!
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
何 考えてんだ！